<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" data-wed-xmlns---tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" data-wed-xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" class="TEI _real"><div class="teiHeader _real"><div class="fileDesc _real"><div class="titleStmt _real"><div class="title _real">Sketch for a medical education</div><div class="author _real">Lind, James, 1736-1812.</div></div><div class="publicationStmt _real"><div class="distributor _real"><div class="name _real">Oxford Text Archive</div><div class="address _real"><div class="addrLine _real">Oxford University Computing Services</div><div class="addrLine _real">13 Banbury Road</div><div class="addrLine _real">Oxford</div><div class="addrLine _real">OX2 6NN</div></div><div class="email _real">ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</div></div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/5689</div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="TCP">K126886.000</div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="BIBNO">CW3308702811</div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="ECMS">0724501800</div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="isbn10">1106026888</div><div class="idno _real" data-wed-type="isbn13">9781106026880</div><div class="availability _real" data-wed-status="restricted"><div class="licence _real" data-wed-target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	  Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
	</div></div></div><div class="sourceDesc _real"><div class="biblFull _real"><div class="titleStmt _real"><div class="title _real">Sketch for a medical education</div><div class="author _real">Lind, James, 1736-1812.</div></div><div class="extent _real">[2],6p. ; 8⁰.</div><div class="publicationStmt _real"><div class="pubPlace _real">[Windsor] :</div><div class="publisher _real">Printed J. Lind M.D. F.R.S. Windsor,</div><div class="date _real">1800.</div></div><div class="notesStmt _real"><div class="note _real">Reproduction of original from the Bodleian Library (Oxford).</div><div class="note _real">English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT199688.</div><div class="note _real">Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</div></div></div></div></div><div class="encodingDesc _real"><div class="projectDesc _real"><div class="p _real">Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </div></div><div class="editorialDecl _real" data-wed-n="4"><div class="p _real">This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</div></div></div><div class="profileDesc _real"><div class="langUsage _real"><div class="language _real" data-wed-ident="eng">eng</div></div></div></div><div class="text _real" data-wed-xml---lang="eng"><div class="front _real"><div class="div _real" data-wed-type="titlepages"><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="1" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="2" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="3" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="4" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="figure _real" data-wed-rend="block"><div class="figDesc _real">silhouette of the bust of a man's head</div></div><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="5" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="p _real">SKETCH FOR A MEDICAL FDUCATON.</div><div class="p _real">Printed J. Lind M.D. F.R.S. Windsor.</div><div class="p _real">1800.</div></div></div><div class="body _real"><div class="pb _real" data-wed-facs="6" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="head _real">SKETCH for a MEDICAL EDUCATION. by J*L. M D. F R S.</div><div class="p _real">After having attained a competent knowledge of the Languages necessary to acquire those Sciences that are requisite to the study of Medicine; and to enable the Student to read and consult the va<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>rious Authors that have written on Phy<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>sic. MATHEMATICS claims his first attention.</div><div class="p _real">Without the knowledge of Mathe<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>matics it is impossible to understand NA<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>TURAL PHILOSOPHY, a Science by which the Laws, and Oeconomy of na<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>ture, and the Human body, can only be understood; as also the many causes that operate upon men and all nature.</div><div class="p _real">ANATOMY being the foundation of medical knowledge, it is therefore to be studied with the greatest care and attention. Its intricacy also requires the aid of the best Professors; and that the Pupil himself practice frequent dissections to attain this most necessary part of a Medical Education. Without the know<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>ledge of Anatomy, it is impossible either
<div class="pb _real" data-wed-n="2" data-wed-facs="7" data-wed-rend="none"></div>to discover the seat, nature, or cure, of Diseases. In Surgery no operation can be performed with safety or with much probability of success to the Patient. From dissections he likewise learns the nature of many hidden Disorders, and when similar symptoms occur to know the Disease under which the Patient la<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>bours. It also enables, the Physician or Surgeon when called upon by a Court of Justice, to determine with certainty whether Death has been occasioned from a natural cause, or from violence; hence he becomes the means of acquitting the innocent, and of condemning the guilty; but if ignorant of Anatomy, perhaps the contrary.</div><div class="p _real">CHEMISTRY is an other necessary part of a Medical Education, as with<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>out a knowledge of it we must ever be ig<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>norant of the various chemical Processes that are constantly going on in the Ani<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>mal oeconomy upon whom depends health or disease, and from a true knowledge of whom, we are greatly instucted how to preserve the first, and to cure the latter also the Physician is liable to give Pre<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>scriptions that cannot be compounded or
<div class="pb _real" data-wed-n="3" data-wed-facs="8" data-wed-rend="none"></div>if they could, He is ignorant of the means by which it can be done. Some efficacious medicines he frequently des<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>troys by his injudicious compositions, while other substances even innocent and inert ones, are rendered injurious and highly poisonous.</div><div class="p _real">A knowledge of the MATERIA-MEDICA is also necessary to every prac<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>titioner of Medicine, without which he is ignorant of the means of cure, notwith<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>standing the Disease is known to him: Also, altho he is acquainted with the powers of a few medicines, he will find himself foiled for want of a more extended knowledge of the Materia-Medica, the constitutions of some people, differing as much from that of mankind in general: as if they were of a different Species. Therefore what proves useful in a dis<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>ease with most people, with some it may be injurious.</div><div class="p _real">The Materia-Medica being an ex<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>tensive Science, requiring the aid of me<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>thod, BOTANY and NATURAL-HIS<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>TORY should therefore make a part of the education of every Physician; the knowledge of them also helps to abridge
<div class="pb _real" data-wed-n="4" data-wed-facs="9" data-wed-rend="none"></div>the study of the Materia-Medica, there being frequently an analogy in the vir<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>tues of bodies of the same Genus.</div><div class="p _real">Lectures on the THEORY of ME<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>DICINE, may now be studied. In this course is also taught PHYSEOLOGY &amp; PATHOLOGY, both absolutely requi<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>site to a Medical Education. Although the different Systems of Physic are im<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>perfect, yet as they serve for a clew to guide and direct a Physician in his pro<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>cedure of Cure, by keeping him from confounding one thing with an other, they are therefore of the greatest utility in the Practice of Medicine; more espe<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>cially as all Practitioners have a natural tendancy to empiricism.</div><div class="p _real">The PRACTICE of PHYSIC is the last, and chief design, of medical study. This part of medical knowledge is to be attained from hearing the Lectu<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>res of eminent Professors, and by reading, but particularly by attending Hospitals, where Clinical Lectures are delivered to the Students, in which are generally given the History of the Disease under which the Patient labours, the purpose proposed, for the administering, of this
<div class="pb _real" data-wed-n="5" data-wed-facs="10" data-wed-rend="none"></div>or that medicine, and their effects up<div class="lb _real" data-wed-rend="hidden" data-wed-type="hyphenInWord"></div>on the Patient pointed out; lastly if the patient dies, the cause of his death is more evidently pointed out and shown to the Students, by the dissecton of the morbid body.</div><div class="div _real" data-wed-type="resume"><div class="head _real">LECTURES attended by J*L. in the University of EDINBURGH.</div><div class="list _real"><div class="item _real">1752 Geometry.</div><div class="item _real">1753 Conic-sections and Algebra,</div><div class="item _real">1754 Natural-Philosophy. Astronomy.</div></div><div class="list _real"><div class="head _real">MEDICINE.</div><div class="item _real">1755 Anatomy. Materia-Medica.</div><div class="item _real">1756 Anatomy. Chemistry. Institutes of Medicine. Botany.</div><div class="item _real">1757 Chemistry. Materia-Medica. Practice of Medicine. Infirmary. Botany.</div><div class="item _real">1758 Chemistry. Anatomy. Practice of Medicine. Infirmary. Clinical-Lectures.</div><div class="item _real">1759 Chemistry. Midwifery. Institutes of Medicine. Practice of Physic. Infirmary. Clinical-Lectures.</div><div class="pb _real" data-wed-n="6" data-wed-facs="11" data-wed-rend="none"></div><div class="item _real">1760 Midwifery. Clinical-Lectures. Materia-Medica.</div></div><div class="list _real"><div class="head _real">In LONDON.</div><div class="item _real">1761 Anatomy.</div><div class="item _real">1764 Chemistry. Anatomy.</div></div><div class="list _real"><div class="head _real">In EDINBURGH.</div><div class="item _real">1767 Institutes of Medicine. Practice of Physic.</div><div class="item _real">1768 September 12, obtained the Degree of Doctor of Physic<div class="note _real" data-wed-place="bottom" data-wed-n="†">vide Thesaurus Medicus Edin. novus Vol. 1. p. 116.</div>.</div></div></div></div><div class="back _real"><div class="div _real" data-wed-type="colophon"><div class="p _real">Printed J. Lind M.D. F.R.S. Windsor.</div><div class="p _real">1800.</div></div></div></div></div>